# Toronto, Canada (+1) 437 2496143 etorres.net@gmail.com

# **Edwin Torres**

Personal Blog Linkedin Profile Github Profile

Summary

I've been coding for about ten years in several Software Roles. I've worked for significant global companies in different industries (Realt State, Payments, Health, Financial). My favorite topics are Web Development, Micro Frontends, InnerSource, and Architecture Design. I love working closely with other Developers to improve their Development Experience every day by creating better documentation or automating repetitive tasks.

## **Technical Skills**

Languages: Java, JavaScript / ES6, TypeScript

Frameworks/Libraries:

Angular 8+, React.js, React Native, Node.js / Deno, TypeScript, Express.js, Webpack, Babel, Gatsby, Single-spa, Firebase, Google APIS, js, CSS/SCSS, Bootstrap, Jasmine, Jest, Karma, Lodash, Moment.js, NPM, YARN

Spring Framework (Core/MVC/Security), Hibernate, JPA, TestNG, Junit, JMeter.

**Other**: Git/Github, Tomcat, MongoDB, PostgreSQL, Oracle, Intellij IDEA, Heroku, Jenkins, TravisCI, Design Systems, Security, Redis, Jira, Confluence, Bitbucket, Postman. JAMStack, PWA, OpenAPI, Docker, Micro Front-ends

# Work Experience

# **ScotiaBank Canada** – Senior Software Developer

Toronto, Canada | Feb 2021 - Present

- Helped to set up the Backstage (a developer portal created by Spotify to improve the developer experience) foundations at Scotiabank.
- Worked with teams in different regions (Colombia, Chile, Mexico, Caribe, and Canada) in the Reuse and Share Program, promoting the reuse mindset and culture.
- Lead an Architecture Community made mainly by developers and architects in different countries.
- Advocated the InnerSource culture, creating documentation, maintaining repositories, and helping people to understand more about this mindset.
- Contributed to the design system libraries, used by more than 100 projects across Scotiabank.

# ScotiaBank Colpatria Front End Lead & Architect Bogotá, Colombia | Jun 2017 - Feb 2021

- Working actively in the Front-End Architecture definitions, best practices, performance, security, accessibility, and solutions for the project.
- Created multiple and re-usable Front-end templates to boost the development speed in every new micro front-end.
- Lead the Front-End team, creating Front-End sync meetings and guidelines.
- Created the React architecture decisions for Digital Factory Colombia.
- Participated actively in the development of digital products for the Colpatria's bank and ScotiaBank using technologies like Spring Boot, Angular 6+ (angular-cli) - Ngrx Store,

- Firebase, TypeScript, SASS, Flexbox, Node.js, Webpack, protractor, serenity.js, jasmine, JWT, Material Design, Google Recaptcha and Progressive Web Apps (PWA).
- Created microservices and new features for the business needs, using a DDD approach. Also participated in the creation of PoC for Micro Front-Ends.
- Collaborated actively with the Global Design System (Canvas) being a Canvas Reps for Colombia to preserve the consistency in the Front-End Projects.

## **Endava** – Senior *Developer*

Bogotá, Colombia | Mar 2017 - June 2017

- Worked as a skilled Front-End developer for global projects using trending stack Front-End technologies like Webpack 2.x, ReactJS, Redux / Redux-Saga, Firebase, ES6 / Babel, SASS, NodeJS, ExpressJS, AVA, JEST, D3, Yarn, Semantic-UI, Jenkins.
- Developed data-driven documents using d3.js to show demographic statistics.

# **Prodigious** – Front-End Engineer

Bogotá, Colombia | May 2016 - Mar 2017

- Created a Mock-Data-Generator application which decreased at least by 60% the time to set up the manual mock data for testing environments.
- Worked in synergy in an 8-10 person team (QA, Front-End, Back-End, Business Analysis) using SCRUM methodology.

# **Prodigious** – Senior Software Engineer

Bogotá, Colombia | Aug 2015 - May 2016

- Participated actively in the architecture committee searching for new ways to enhance the Software internals process.
- Presented success demos to the final client of the features developed by the Team every Sprint ending (SCRUM methodology).

# Conexia SA – Semi Senior Developer

Bogotá, Colombia | Sep 2014 - Jul 2015

- Participated successfully in the application refactor for Emssanar and Saludcoop EPS in an 8-10 person team.
- Supported the QA Team, teaching the best practices to test the stories and re-test the bugs using JIRA.

## El Tiempo – Software Developer Engineer Bogotá, Colombia | Mar 2013 – Sep 2014

- Implemented the Spring Framework upgrade from 2.5 to 3.x version in 2 months, improving the readability code and removing more than 80% of the bugs in the project.
- Formalized the development process using the SCRUM methodology, which improved the communication between clients, business analysis, and developers.
- Led the Metrocuadrado.com Team (4 people) for 3 months. Here I was involved in lead tasks, such as daily meetings, and defining priorities for the clients.

## Education

**ECCI** – B.S, System Engineering

Jun 2008 - May 2014

## **Honors and Activities**

ECCI Programming Marathons

2009, 2010, 2011